According to Kepler data, just 11 cargo
vessels passed through Bab al-Mandab on
July 26th, the lowest number in many
months. The strait has not been
completely closed, and some tankers are
still willing to take the risk. Others,
however, are turning north and taking
the long route around Africa. That
journey adds roughly 10,000 nautical
miles and can take an additional 34
days. The extra transport cost alone is
estimated at more than $5 million per
voyage, on top of roughly $1 million in
Suez Canal fees and higher insurance
premiums.
The Houthis' entry into the war,
therefore, complicates Donald Trump's
position even further. The Middle
Eastern crisis now affects not one, but
two critical straits through which,
before the war, a combined 24 million
barrels of oil passed [music] every day.